A Guide to the Papers of the Dabney Family and Virginius Dabney, 1735-1982
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Dabney Family and Virginius Dabney 1735-1982
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7690-ah
This collection consists of ca. 600 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This accession was given to the Library by Mr. Virginius Dabney of Richmond, Virginia, on September 19, 1983.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Virginius Dabney contain extensive correspondence carried on by Dabney as editor of the Richmond Times-Dispatch, in his personal life, and as a Pulitzer Prize- winning author. Other materials deal with his books such as Below the Potomac, The Dry Messiah, and Liberalism in the South, and much useful material collected as research material for these books is present. There is extensive material on the American Society of Newspaper Editors which Dabney served in various capacities including president. A great deal of useful material on race relations, African Americans, the N.A.A.C.P., etc., is present. Recent political history of Virginia is strongly represented in Dabney's correspondence as editor of Virginia's leading newspaper, and in his personal correspondence with figures such as Senator A. Willis Robinson, Francis Pickens Miller, and Senator Carter Glass.
This collection consists of ca. 600 items, 1735-1982, papers of the Dabney and related families of Virginia. Included in the collection are correspondence, manuscripts of books and articles, a diary and a journal, legal papers, printed material, memorabilia, and photographs.
The first series of papers, 1735 and 1790-1918, 269 items, includes papers of the Dabney and the related Carr, Davis, and Terrell families. The correspondence, 1790-1908, is between various members of the Dabney family and their relatives concerning various topics. Correspondence of the Davis, Terrell, and Carr families, 1790-1892, is primarily Civil War correspondence. Pre-Civil War correspondents include Samuel Terrell (d. 1798), [Lucy Ann?] Terrell (fl. 1812), Eugene Davis (1822-1894), and Lucy Davis (1827-1859). The earliest letter, July 7, Kentucky and opportunities there, Indians, and a convention to be held in Danville regarding separation of the Lower Mississippi Valley from the United States in response to the possible ratification of the Jay-Cardoqui Treaty (August 29, 1787). Another letter from Lucy Ann Terrell to Virginia Terrell, July 18, 1812, concerns the choice of "Uncle Carr" as president of the College of William and Mary. Another letter, from Lucy Davis to her mother, Mary B. Blackford, November 5, 1848, describes in detail the death of twenty-three year-old Patsy Davis, wife of Eugene Davis, and her burial in the University of Virginia cemetery. Fifteen letters in the Carr, Davis, and Terrell correspondence date from the Civil War and include letters written by Captain Eugene Davis; Mary Jane Terrell Davis (1803-1879), mother of Eugene Davis; Richard Terrell Davis (1830-1892), a Confederate Eugene Davis; and F.E.G. Carr, lieutenant Commander, Company K, 30th Regiment, Virginia Volunteers. Topics mentioned in these letters include news of the deaths of acquaintances and relatives; family matters; the hiring out of slaves; slaves who served as personal servants to men in the army; Captain Eugene Davis' command by F.E.G. Carr; the procurement of clothes and shoes for soldiers; a Union army charge on Fort Harrison; a hasty Confederate retreat following a Union attack; desolation around Fredericksburg in 1863; and Henry Wise. Several letters mention life in Charlottesville of Virginia for the wounded; the use of Alexander Garrett's house as a hospital for typhoid patients; and the burial of seventy-five dead in a trench outside the University cemetery. The post-Civil War letters in the Carr, Davis, and Terrell correspondence, 1888-1892, are from A. Moore, Jr., E.W. Saunders, and Joseph Bryan to Eugene Davis. The letters from Bryan to Davis mention family matters, an invitation to visit the Richmond exposition where the Charlottesville Woolen Mills had a loom in operation, and an invitation to stay with Bryan during the unveiling of the statue of Robert E. Lee in Richmond.
Correspondence of the Dabney family, 1856-1908, follows, and includes letters of Virginius Dabney (1835-1894), Maria (Heath) Dabney, Dabney's first wife; Elizabeth Anna Heath, mother of Maria (Heath) Dabney. Topics discussed in these letters include the marriage of Virginius Dabney and Maria Heath; their library of over 600 volumes; Dabney's New York Latin School; the publication of Virginius Dabney's Don Miff and Gold That Did Not Glitter; Susan Dabney Smedes' Memorials of a Southern Planter; and Richard Heath Dabney's The Causes of the French Revolution; efforts to remove Latin as a requirement for the B.A. and M.A. degrees at the University of Virginia; and the appointment of Richard Heath Dabney as full professor of historical science at the University of Virginia. A letter from Woodrow Wilson to Dabney, December 5, 1897, regarding the letter's promotion is present as well. A 144-page transcript of the letters to Virginius Dabney and his family, 1886, regarding the publication of his book, Don Miff, completes the correspondence.
The manuscripts include a draft of Don Miff and a copy of an article, "A Mighty Hunter Before the Lord," by Virginius Dabney; three manuscripts regarding the Civil War and bird life by Susan Dabney Smedes; and four manuscripts by Richard Heath Dabney on various topics.
In addition, there is a diary, 1882-1883, kept by Richard Heath Dabney while studying in Germany at the Universities of Munich and Berlin, in which he records descriptions of his studies and his professors and friends. Another journal, August, 1890, titled "Notes on the life of Virginius Dabney" records Dabney's memories of growing up at "Burleigh", his parents Mississippi home, before the Civil War.
The legal papers include documents regarding Memorials of a Southern Planter, Don Miff, and The Causes of the French Revolution. Also included are a petition supporting Richard Heath Dabney's appointment as professor of historical science and Thomas Carr's will, May 25, 1735.
The printed material includes several advertisements for schools and books, 1871-1899, and numerous newspaper clippings, 1835-1909, regarding the Dabney family and the University of Virginia. This series concludes with memorabilia and photographs. Among the photographs are pictures of various members of the Dabney family as well as of Woodrow Wilson and Jack Eggleston. A scrapbook, 1887-1891, containing newspaper clippings regarding Don Miff and Gold That did Not Glitter completes this series.
The second series, papers of Virginius Dabney (1901- ) includes correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, and miscellaneous items. The correspondence, 1909-1917, is comprised of letters written by Dabney to his family while visiting relatives and while visiting his uncle, Thomas S. Dabney (Lloyd d'Aubigné) in Sèvres, France. Also included are numerous letters written by Dabney while a student at Episcopal High School The manuscripts include numerous articles by Dabney published in journals and magazines as well as the final drafts of a bicentennial history of the Virginia Society of the Cincinnati and Richmond: The Story of a City. Miscellaneous material includes: Dabney's student reports from Episcopal High School, 1914-1917; genealogical material regarding the Dabney family; printed articles by Dabney; an award presented to Dabney in 1975; programs; a poster; and newspaper and magazine clippings regarding Dabney. Photographs of Dabney, 1901-1982, including some of him with Winston Churchill, Richard Nixon, Dean Acheson, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Douglas S. Freeman, and Harry F. Byrd, Sr., follow the miscellaneous material. An oversize copy of a survey of "Burleigh", Dabney's great- grandparents' home, completes the collection.
Organization
The collection has been divided into two series: I.) Papers of the Dabney family, 1735 (1790-1918), and II.) Papers of Virginius Dabney, 1901-1982. Series I has been divided into the following subseries: correspondecne; manuscripts; diaries; legal papers; printed material; and memorabilia and photographs. Series II has been dvided into correspondence, manuscripts, miscellaneous, and photographs. Each subseries is in chronological order except for the manuscripts and photographs which are in alphabetical order by titile and/or name.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence of the Davis, Terrell, and Carr families 1790-1892, 27 items. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of the Dabney family 1856-1886, 1887-1888, 1889-1908, 52 items. 3 folders. (Box 1)
  - Typescript of letters re Don Miff1886, 1 item. (Box 1)
- Manuscript
  - Draft of Don Miff, by Virginius Dabney n.d., 1 item. (Box 1)
  - "A Mighty Hunter Before the Lord," by Virginius Dabney n.d., 2 items. (Printed) (Box 1)
  - Manuscript, "Observations of Bird Life...", by Susan Dabney Smedes n.d., 1 item. (Box 1)
  - Manuscript, "Recollections of the War," by Susan Dabney Smedes n.d., 1 item. (Box 1)
  - Manuscript, "A Woman's Recollection of Some Things During the Civil War," by Susan Dabney Smedes n.d., 1 item. (Box 1)
  - "Athleticism," by Richard Heath Dabney 1911 March 9, 1 item. (Box 1)
  - "The Elevation of History to the Rank of a Science," by Richard Heath Dabney n.d., 1 item. (Box 1)
  - Speech, "Germany's Dream of Dominion," by Richard Heath Dabney n.d., 1 item. (Box 1)
  - "The Huguenot Element in Virginia's Population," by Richard Heath Dabney n.d., 1 item. (Box 2)
- Diary
  - Diary of Richard Heath Dabney 1882-1883 (Box 2)
  - Journal of Richard Heath Dabney 1890 Aug. (Box 2)
- Legal Papers
  - Will of Thomas Carr (electrostatic copy) 1735 May 25, 1 item (Box 2)
  - Contract between Richard Heath Dabney and Henry Holt and Co. re The Causes of the French Revolution1887 Dec. 27, 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Memorandum of agreement re publication of Don Miff1889 Jun. 29, 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Petition supporting Richard Heath Dabney's appointment as Professor of Historical Science at the University of Virginia [1897], 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Receipts and royalty statements for Memorials of a Southern Planter, by Susan Dabney Smedes 1899, 1907, n.d., 4 items. (Box 2)
- Printed Material
  - Newspaper clippings re The Causes of the French Revolution, by Richard Heath Dabney1886-1888, n.d., 20 items. (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings re Memorials of a Southern Planter, by Susan Dabney Smedes 1887-1895, n.d., 59 items. (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings by or re Virginius Dabney 1892-1938, n.d., 8 items. (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings re Richard Heath Dabney's appointment to Chair of History and Political Economy at The University of Virginia 1897-1899, n.d., 4 items. (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings re attempts to remove Latin requirement for B.A. and M.A. at the University of Virginia 1907, n.d., 4 items. (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clipping, "What is the Future of Football?" 1909 Dec. 4, 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clipping re death of Elizabeth Anna Heath n.d., 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Extracts from the Richmond Enquirer re dinner for Thomas S. Dabney 1835 Sept. 22, 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Catalogue of Loudoun School, Middleburg 1871 (Box 2)
  - Printed advertisement for Don Miff[1889], 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Advertisement for Memorials of a Southern Planter, by Susan Dabney Smedes 1899, n.d., 5 items. (Box 2)
  - L. d'Aubigné's school brochure n.d., 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Advertisement for The Causes of the French Revolution, by Richard Heath Dabney n.d., 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Invitation, menu, and keep-sake for dinner given by George T. Seabury 1887 Oct. 27. Nov. 10, 3 items. (Box 2)
  - Ticket for reading of Don Miffn.d., 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Photograph: Anna Noland Dabney 1911, 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Photographs: Lily Heth Dabney 1900, n.d., 2 items. (Box 2)
  - Photographs: Richard Heath Dabney 1890-1912, n.d., 9 items. (Box 2)
  - Photographs: Thomas L. Dabney (L. d'Aubigné) [1911-1918], n.d., 21 items. (Box 2)
  - Photograph: Thomas S. Dabney n.d., 2 items. (Box 2)
  - Photograph: Virginius Dabney n.d., 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Photograph: Ward Dabney n.d., 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Photograph: Capt. Jack Eggleston n.d., 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Photograph: Susan Dabney Smedes n.d., 1 item. (Box 3)
  - Photograph: Woodrow Wilson n.d., 1 item. (Box 3)
  - Photograph: Susan Dabney Winston n.d., 1 item. (Box 3)
  - Photograph: unidentified n.d., 1 item. (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings from scrapbook 1887-1891, n.d., 13 items. (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1886-1887, n.d., 1 item. (Box 3)
- Virginius Dabney Papers, 1901-1982 Correspondence
  - Letters from Virginius Dabney to family 1909, 10 items. (Box 3)
  - Letters from Virginius Dabney to family 1910-1911, 12 items. (Box 3)
  - Letters from Virginius Dabney to family from Sèvres, France 1912, 13 items. (Box 3)
  - Letters from Virginius Dabney to family 1913, 10 items. (Box 3)
  - Letters from Virginius Dabney to family 1914, 27 items. (Box 3)
  - Letters from Virginius Dabney to family 1915 Jan-Dec., 1916 Jan.-Dec., 132 items. 5 folders. (Box 3)
  - Letters from Virginius Dabney to family 1917, n.d., 45 items. (Box 4)
- Manuscripts
  - Manuscript for bicentennial history of Virginia Society of the Cincinnati n.d. (Box 4)
  - Research material, correspondence, and manuscript for "The Human Side of Woodrow Wilson" 1956, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Research material and manuscript for "Is the U.S. Responsible for the Cold War?" 1961, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Research material, correspondence, and manuscripts for article re Jack Jouett's ride 1961-1966, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Research material, correspondence, and manuscript for article re Virginia Historical Society 1951-1961, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Final draft, Richmond: The Story of a Cityn.d., 2 folders. (Box 4)
  - Final draft, Richmond: The Story of a Cityn.d., 3 folders. (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous
  - Printed articles by Virginius Dabney 1939-1946 (Box 5)
  - Genealogical material re the Dabney family 1900-1978, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Epsiscopal High School reports for Virginius Dabney 1914-1917 (Box 5)
  - Poster announcing speech by Virginius Dabney 1952 May 22 (Box 5)
  - Programs 1958-1979, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings re Virginius Dabney 1966, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Virginia Social Science Association Distinguished Service Award 1975 Apr. 12 (Box 5)
- Photographs
  - Photographs of Virginius Dabney ca. 1901-1919 (Box 5)
  - Photographs: Virginius Dabney ca. 1914-1919, 1938-1949, 1950-1959, 1970-1982, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Survey of "Burleigh", w/TLS, 1961 July 27, John C. Parker to Virginius Dabney 1860 July 7 (Box 5)